Developer & Systems Administrator

Specialty Expertise within Hosting and Communications Technology Environments

Talented IT strategist, architect, administrator, and solution developer, with cross platform expertise (e.g. Linux/UNIX/Windows/MS-DOS), diverse industry experience, a customer focused mindset, and multi-lingual fluency (e.g. Perl, Python, HTML, JavaScript, PHP). RedHat Certified Engineer and MySQL Core certified with vast skill set across a full spectrum of systems administration and developer functions. Fast learner, effective communicator, logical thinker, and respected project leader.

Achievement highlights include ground up design of robust, fully integrated networks (up to 1,000 users); delivery of 50% increases in efficiency and double digit improvements in system uptimes (from 86% to 99.9%); and creative, cost effective, and timely problem solving of multiple of issues (e.g. system security, downed server/hard drives, data storage inefficiencies, remote connectivity, high speed wireless technology, technical training/support, and workflow automation).

KEY KNOWLEDGE AREAS

Linux/Unix Technical Infrastructure Network Design Network Administration Web Development Strategic Planning Disaster Recovery Troubleshooting System Security
Technical Support
Systems Implementation
Systems Migration

TECHNOLOGY SUMMARY

Networking: WANs/LANs/MANs/VLANs, TCP/IP, Cabling, Routers, Switches, Hubs, VPNs/IPSEC,

serial interfaces (T1 et al.), ISDN, PRI, Frame Relay, NAT, Wireless Networking/WiFi

(802.11a/b/g), Firewalls (Sonicwall/PIX)

Systems: Linux (from 2.2.x to current), MS Windows, Solaris, Cisco IOS, FreeBSD, BSDi, MS-DOS

Languages: Perl, Python, HTML, JavaScript, PHP, bash, C/C++ (basic), Java (basic) Hardware: x86/x86-64, SPARC, MIPS, Adaptec, LSI Megaraid, Dell PowerEdge

Software: Legato NetWorker, GNU Tools, Apache, XFree86, Bind, ProFTPd, SSH, Postfix,

IMAP/POP servers, VMWare, IIS, Windows DNS, MS Office, Star/Open Office, Abi-Word, Gnumeric, Mozilla, clustering (MOSIX), Gnome, KDE, Citrix Metaframe 1.8/XP,

Gimp, Photoshop, PageMaker, QuarkXPress

Databases: MySQL, Postgre SQL, MSSQL

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Rackspace:

Leading Hosting Provider San Antonio, TX

Jul 2007-...

Applications Developer 3

Lead backup migration effort from Legato to Commvault. Developed application to automate 90% of migration and created guidelines for manual QC by contractors. Became intimately familiar with Commvault database in short time frame to be able to speak intelligently with Commvault Development staff in requesting features and avenues of achieving them.

Wrote Commvault read only API allowing other application developers to extract information from Commvault databases. Paved the way for cli tools that presented data in a user friendly manner.

Provide mentoring and guidance to other developers at Rackspace.

Placemark Investments:

Portfolio Management Company Addison, TX

Sep 2006-Jul 2007

Systems Engineer

Upgrade and redesign company Active Directory to provide a scalable and redundant management and authentication system for Windows and Linux/Unix Desktops and Servers. Integrate Samba file servers with AD authentication and posix ACLs for authentication and file security to provide file sharing and application hosting services. Manage WSUS 3.0 server for centralized deployment of

Redesign company IP address space from legacy single RFC 1918 class C to scalable multiple subnet network also using space from RFC 1918. Assist with re-setup of OpenBSD pf firewall for the new network scheme using CARP and VLAN interfaces for redundancy and port utilization efficiency. Firewall and network redesigns provides finer control over access to sensitive information from different networks.

Designed and oversaw installation of Mini-DC in office server room to house local servers and production staging area. Gathered power requirements and specified centralized battery backup options. Met with vendors and received bids for various integration services (electrical, cabling, ...). Installed cabinets and cabinet PDUs.

Provide assistance and advice to junior team members including help desk personnel. Ensured that junior team members were involved in the troubleshooting process when assisting to foster their technical development.

Rackspace Managed Hosting:

Leading Managed Hosting Provider San Antonio, TX

Oct 2005-Aug 2006

SMB Service Innovation - Programmer

Develop tools, scripts, and applications allowing Support and Managed Backup Techs to preform their duties more efficiently. Notable achievements include:

Deployment system and Python module to run commands on a set of servers (Unix/Linux/Windows) automatically while collecting output. Output stored in MySQL database for reporting and data mining.

Backup failure alerts, create alerts in a centralized console when customer backup fails. Eliminated manual process of harvesting failures from emails. Allows tracking of backup failure history.

Custom backup usage reporting. Collects and emails backup usage daily to group of customers which subscribe to service. Based on active push from the NetWorker backup system, eliminating the need to monitor log files to collect data passively.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (continued)

Windows 2003 Service Pack 1 Updater for Dell 2650 and 2850 servers. Stepped through applying bios patches, OpenManage upgrade, and service pack 1 installation.

May 2005-Oct 2005

SMB Managed Backup Team Leader

Provide leadership and direction for 8 member SMB Managed Backup Team. Identify, assign, and monitor progress of team projects. Interface extensively with other departments to architect solutions for customer backups. Ensure team continuity and resolve issues. Empower and advise team members to resolve customer issues without escalation where possible. Provide guidance and mentoring to team members to ensure customer service.

Oct 2004-May 2005

Managed Backup Administrator

Monitor and troubleshoot Rackspace Managed Backup offering, utilizing Legato NetWorker. Configure, schedule, and verify new customer backups, interfacing with other departments as necessary (Networking, Support, DCOPS). Advanced troubleshooting of backup and restore failures using vendor documentation, knowledge-base, and/or support services. Perform data restoration upon customer request. Organize regular audits of backup configurations to ensure quality of service, Resolve escalated customer issues and provide technical advice and direction to Backup Technicians. Advise customers on best backup practices to maximize uptime and reduce restore time.

Create and manage bash and Perl scripts to automate interfacing with Net-Worker. Created several scripts for group control and save set information. Wrote and maintained semi-automated script to collect information from CRM application and create NSR Client definitions for input to NetWorker. Worked with internal CRM developers to create xmlrpc interface to CRM, reducing errors generated by screen scrapping.

Mar 2004-Oct 2004

Level II Support Administrator

Interface and provide support to Rackspace Customers on a daily basis through telephone and ticketing system. Support topics include, but not limited to: Apache configuration including v-hosting and mass v-hosting, troubleshooting and performance tuning; Sendmail/Postfix/Qmail configuration including best practices, virtual address setup and walk-through, proper mail configuration to prevent unnecessary mail blocks; MySQL performance tuning including data restructuring and query optimization suggestions, upgrade benefits of newer versions of MySQL (ex. Query Caching).

Operating systems supported included: Linux (RedHat, Debian, SuSE, Gentoo), Solaris, FreeBSD, Windows 2k/2k3.

Jun 2003–Mar 2004 Dec 2002–Jun 2003 **Data Center Operations Team Leader**

Data Center Operations Tech

Provide fanatical service and support to Rackspace customers. Interface and coordinate with multiple departments to troubleshoot and provision hardware. Monitor and troubleshoot customer servers and network devices.

Assume Technical Guide web administration duties, an all inclusive Data Center Operations knowledge-base. Ensure accuracy of all submissions and QC/Review current documentation. Review all code, to affirm cross platform/browser usability. Set guidelines and policies for article submissions.

Implemented centralized authentication system for web applications developed and used in the Data Center Operations Department. QC, modify, or suggest changes to web applications to provide a secure interface to the centralized authentication system.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (continued)

Develop projects that reduce the amount of unneeded paperwork. Develop projects that allow Data Center Technicians to work smarter; analyze requirements from management and implement solutions utilizing processing power first, man power second.

Create custom jumpstart system for installing Solaris on customer's servers. Automated all aspects of install, including installation of patch cluster, setup of DiskSuite mirrored root and swap slices, network configuration (including aliases and private-net), modified started services to reduce security issues, and created initial users.

Mustang/Carrera Communications:

Provider of turnkey IT solutions / CLEC San Antonio, TX

Jun 2000-Oct 2002 Network / Systems Administrator

> Interface extensively with clients to perform comprehensive needs analysis and explain features/benefits/drawbacks of various solution options. Design and install customer focused networks for small to mid-size companies; analyze current systems and recommend performance enhancing infrastructure changes; research products and vendors for customers; and reconfigure, install, and troubleshoot servers and network services.

> Skyrocketed system uptime from an average of 86% to 99.9% following leadership of Linux migration. Troubleshot and resolved challenges of varying complexities to reverse prior history of hard drive crashes, system slowdowns, security breaches, tenuous coding, downed server, data storage inefficiencies, and applications stalls.

> Completed ground up network design (up to 1,000 local/remote users) and/or system and network enhancements for diverse industry clients (e.g. funeral services, health care, high tech, manufacturing, property management, investment banking, and real estate) within a broad range of technical environments (Windows, Linux, BSD).

> Rapidly resolved business crippling issues for clients with outdated technology (e.g. BSDI 2.0 Pentium Pro), crashed hard drives, and malfunctioning motherboards. Restored systems and designed safeguards and back-ups that won rave reviews and frequent referral business from clients.

> Augmented vulnerable network and redesigned poorly designed firewall for investment banking client unaware that all of its transactions and confidential customer files were exposed to the public.

> Redesigned multiple networks substituting public IP's with private IPs, limiting peer-to-peer network usage and saving on bandwidth costs. Results included growth enabling, highly redundant, consolidated networks delivering efficiency/functionality improvements of at least 50%.

GTE – Now Verizon Communications:

Major world provider of high growth communications services Austin, TX Level 1 Tech Support Rep

Provided first contact technical support to end users as member of outsourced help desk team for Internet Appliance ISP. Troubleshot connectivity issues; addressed customer questions regarding I-Opener appliance use and the Internet; provided patient, step-by-step solutions to users with divergent technical backgrounds; escalated problems as appropriate; and hand selected as primary trainer for Level 1 new hires.

Resolved approximately 90% of customer issues on the first call.

Feb 2000-Jun 2000

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE (continued)

Became self taught expert in I-Opener by disassembling device in home lab to determine modem hardware, components, hardware layout, and system functionality. Efforts enabled enhanced customer support and better ticket documentation and led to frequent requests from Level 2 reps for product specific information and assistance.

Saved countless hours of Level 2 reps time and sped solution delivery for customers by resolving many calls that otherwise would have been escalated. Earned a reputation for on-target RMA recommendations due to ability to quickly identify defective appliance hardware.

FPA Medical Management / Optimal IS:

Physician practice management organization San Antonio, TX

Aug 1997-Aug 1998

MIS Intern

Selected for team providing IS outsourcing and turnkey IS department implementation. Repaired systems and hardware, gave help desk support, and assisted with large network upgrades (5,000–10,0000 users).

Created content, design, and coding for company's first corporate intranet. Incorporated interactive features to encourage upward communications, knowledge sharing, and key message delivery.

Initiated and implemented fully automated inventory solution that enabled tracking or approximately 250K pieces of equipment scattered across ten locations. Designed labeling system for processors and RAM as additional precautionary measure to protect close to 3 million dollars in inventory.

Axiom Business Services:

Business brokerage firmSan Antonio, TX

Jun 1996-Aug 1998

System Administrator

Maintained small company systems, designed and printed marketing material, and created original artwork and company logo to extend business identity / image.

EDUCATION & LICENSURE

Iowa State University

1999 Bachelor's Degree Program in MIS

Hand selected by ISU president as one of 20 (out of 5,000) students for **ISU Presidential Leader-ship Program**.

Certifications

2001 Cisco Certified Network Associate

2003 Red Hat Certified Engineer

2004 MySQL Core Certification

1997

OF NOTE